Now let us come to the video about higher-order
functions specifically for lists, as a more
interesting application than the artificial
examples I have shown you before when I wanted
to make the syntax available (and explain
it).
So, I say on lists here, but as in previous
parts of the lecture, this is just for examples'
sake.
Similar functions to the ones I'm going to
show you now (and you're going to use in the
next exercises, probably) are available for
other data types as well.
So, lists are just a stand-in, here, for generally
structured data types.
And this approach of using higher-order functions,
defining higher-order functions and working
with them, is valid and useful for other data
types as well: for trees or other things that
are yet to come, or will not even be covered
in this lecture, but that are useful in practice.
So, lists, just because lists are so simple,
and we can directly use them.
Let's look at a first example, a first higher-order
function on lists.
This is this function that has a somewhat
strange name, maybe.
So, maybe it is not immediately obvious why
this is called "foldl1".
There is some systematics behind this because
there are other versions without the "1",
and there are versions with an "r" instead
of the "l" here.
Let's, for the moment, accept this strange
name and look at what the function does.
And then later, we can discuss and see what
other versions there are.
So, what is this doing?
First, let's look at the type.
It is a polymorphic type.
And in that, we can, of course, see the higher-orderness
here.
Because the first argument is a function,
namely, a binary function on some type.
We have a type variable "a" here.
So, "a to a to a" for whatever "a" is.
So, for some type, we have a binary function
here.
And actually, down here, we also see that
it is expected to be left-associative (or
to be used in that way).
But that is not something that the type expresses.
The type simply says that we have a binary
function and then we have a list of "a"s,
so, a list of elements of the kind on which
this function can operate.
And the outcome will also be one of those
things.
Well, not necessarily one of the elements
from that specific list, but something of
the same type of the things that we have in
the list (and the things that this function
can operate on).
And what does this function do?
This is not seen in the type directly, but
it is explained here.
So, it puts a function (an operator), namely
this one, which should be left-associative
(or be used left-associatively, as we will
see), and puts it between all elements of
a non-empty list.
So, we expect that this list is non-empty,
and this is actually what the "1" stands for.
The "l" stands for "left", and the "1" stands
for "at least one element".
We won't use this function for an empty list.
And the function puts an operator between
all elements of the non-empty list, in a left-associative
fashion.
So, what does this mean?
Let's look at an example.
Let's say we want to compute the sum of a
list.
We have a list, say, of integers.
So, then "a" will be Int; and we have a list;
and we want to compute the sum.
What does this mean?
Basically, taking a list and computing the
sum of it means to put the "+" symbol between
all neighbouring elements.
So, we want to compute 1 + 2 + 3 + 4, which
is exactly what is explained here: putting
a certain operator there.
So, "+" is actually associative, so it doesn't
really matter how we bracket here.
For other operators like "-", of course, this
could make a difference, whether we are left-
or right-associative; whether we consider
this to be computing this first, and then
this, and then for the whole list, or whether
we want to compute somehow differently, like
first this, then this, and then the whole
expression.
For "+", it doesn't matter.
So, computing the sum of a list, however long
it might be, is simply described by putting
a "+" between all neighbouring elements.
If you recall our earlier discussion in the
previous week when we had this convenient
"sum" function and I said: even if we didn't
have the "sum" function available on lists,
we could simply write it with very few keystrokes.
Basically, these are the keystrokes that we
need.
So, this is the "sum" function.
It takes some list and puts "+" between all
neighbouring elements.
That's what summing the elements of a list
means.
And the "foldl1" function is polymorphic.
That's why we can use it so easily.
If we had something like a list of Boolean
values, then we cannot add them, but we can
maybe conjunct them, or disjunct them, with
"and" and "or".
And then we can use the same polymorphic function,
just with a different operator here.
We have polymorphism, and we have higher-orderness,
and they combine to very nice uses here.
And we will see more functions of that kind,
and applications of this principle, this combination
of polymorphism and higher-orderness.
Here is another example of a higher-order
function on lists.
And again, while as shown here it's a function
on lists, the same principle is applicable
to other data structures.
So, for other data structures that contain
elements of some type like trees, dictionaries,
or something not just list-structured, we
will also have a "map" function, not with
exactly the same name, but with the same ideas.
So, what does "map" mean?
As written here, it's a polymorphic function
and it's a higher-order function.
It is parameterized over whatever function.
So, the argument here is very general.
It's a function from something to something.
So, "a" and "b" are possibly different types
(because they use different type variables).
And then what do we get?
The second argument is a list of "a"s and
it returns a list of "b"s.
What does the function do?
It applies this function to all elements of
a list and gives back a list with the changed
elements.
Of course, they are not changed in place.
We don't want to change this list and turn
the "a"s into "b"s.
No, we give *in* a list of "a"s, and we get
*out* a list of "b"s which will be exactly
as long, but each element here is the result
of applying this function to the corresponding
element here.
So, we have now a new list which is a list
of "b"s and is the result of this function
(whatever was the first argument to the "map"
call) on the corresponding elements from
here.
How could we use this?
For example, we could call it with the "even"
predicate on some list of integers.
So, let's discuss what would happen here.
The function "even" goes from Int to Bool.
In this case, "a" would be Int and "b" would
be Bool, which means that the second argument
should be a list of Ints, which is the case
here.
Then the outcome would be a list of Bools.
And, well, which Bools?
For each element here, we would apply the
"even" predicate, so checking whether the
number is even or not, and accumulating the
outcomes in the list.
So, the outcome of this call here will be a
list with 10 elements.
The first element is False because "1" is
not even.
The second element of the result will be True,
because the second element from this list
is "2", which is even, and so on.
We have False, True, False, True, False, True,
False, True, False, True.
Overall, 10 Boolean values.
And each of them is the result of the check
for evenness of the corresponding element
from the original list.
That is this line.
But of course, since the function is polymorphic,
we don't have to apply it to numbers or Booleans.
We can apply it, for example, to Pictures.
For example, "a" and "b" could both be instantiated
with Picture, then you would have to give
in a function from Pictures to Pictures.
Well, let's think of the CodeWorld library.
For example, "dilated 5" is a function from
Pictures to Pictures.
Namely, it takes a Picture and scales it by
a factor 5 in both x and y directions.
So, this is a partial application.
It's a function.
Actually, "dilated" takes a number and a Picture
and gives a Picture.
So, if we apply it partially to just a number,
then we get a function from Picture to Picture.
That is something we can pass in here, if
"a" and "b" are both "Picture".
Then we have to give a list of Pictures.
So, let's say we have three Pictures: pic1,
pic2, pic3.
Then we can pass this in.
And what would be the outcome?
Again, a list of Pictures because "b" will
also be Picture in this case.
And what is the outcome list?
It's a list of three Pictures, which are these
three, but each of them is scaled in both
x and y direction by 5.
This is expressing: take this list of Pictures,
and for each of them, scale in this way.
And that is a very brief way to express this.
And another example:
The so-called "filter" function.
A slightly different type.
What are the ingredients now?
Again, we have a function.
But now it's not a function from "a" to some
"b" (to anything).
It's a function of type from "a" to Bool.
So, it is a predicate.
The "a" is still polymorphic.
But the outcome of this function type is specifically
Bool.
Which was allowed in the previous case with
the "map" function, but it was not enforced
there.
There, "b" could be anything.
Then, again, we get a list of "a"s, so, of
the things to which this predicate (this function)
can be applied.
And the outcome is a list of "a"s.
Previously, it was a list of "b"s because
we outputted the results of applying the function
to elements from here.
Now for the filter- instead of the map-function,
we instead return a list of "a"s.
Which "a"s are this?
Which "a" elements will this be?
The ones from this list which satisfy whatever
predicate is given here (whatever function
from "a" to Bool is given here).
So, this could be a shorter list than this
one, because some elements from this list
might not satisfy this predicate, and then
they are discarded.
Let's think about using this with the "even"
predicate again.
In the previous slide, I had "map" and "even"
and [1,2,...,10], and then the outcome was
[False, True, False, True, ...].
Ten elements to ten Boolean values, namely,
False, True, etc., because 1 is not even,
but 2 is even, 3 is not even, etc.
What would happen if we apply "filter" and
"even"?
What does it say?
Take the elements from that list [1..10] which
satisfy the predicate.
So, the ones to which the function applied
gives False would now not be kept.
So, we don't keep 1, 3, 5, etc.
The other ones are kept.
And we don't output True for them, because
we don't output Bool.
The output is the elements themselves.
So, while "map even [1..10]" gives [False,
True, False, True, ...], "filter even [1..10]"
gives [2,4,6,8,10].
We get the list of numbers which satisfy the
predicate.
This was one example, with the "even" predicate.
We can think of other examples.
Let's take the "isPalindrome" function that
we used in the slides (and you also programmed
a version of it in the exercises).
And let's say we have a "completeDictionary",
as a list of Strings.
And we want to know which of the words in
our dictionary are palindromes.
We simply have to filter that complete dictionary
by this isPalindrome-predicate.
So, this would be a list of Strings, and "isPalindrome"
is a function from String to Bool, so the
outcome would be again a list of Strings,
namely, only those words from the dictionary
which are palindromes.
Or let's say we have something like "bonusPercentageList",
as Double values, and we want to keep only
those which are greater than 50%.
Then we could pass this section, this anonymous
function, to the filter-function.
So, the predicate would be from Double to Bool
(because that is exactly what this is doing:
checking for a Double whether it's greater
than 0.5), this would be a list of Doubles
(the bonusPercentageList), and the outcome
would be a possibly shorter list of Doubles,
namely, only those kept that are greater than
50%.
And again, when I say "It selects list elements",
that doesn't mean it changes this list.
This is a list which comes in.
It is the input.
And out comes another list, which is probably,
in most cases, a bit shorter because some elements
will not be selected.
So, we don't delete something from the list.
We give back a new list which has fewer elements.
Now we could ask ourselves how "map" and "filter"
are defined.
Actually, you should be able to come up with
this on your own.
Namely, "map" and "filter", applying a function
to each element of a list or selecting elements
from a list according to some predicate/property;
that was exactly what we have been using list
comprehension for, so far.
Indeed, you could think of what you see on
this slide as the definitions of "map" and
"filter".
The "map"-function takes a function, takes
a list, and what does it do?
It selects each element from the list, applies
f to it, and accumulates the outcomes in a
list.
This is not actually how "map" is defined
in the standard library, because there are
different and more general ways to do this
(which will also be applicable to other types,
as I mentioned).
But for the specific case of lists, you could
think of "map" as being defined like this.
So, whenever, so far, we wrote something like
this, we could also have used the map-function.
You couldn't have used that sometimes, because
that was excluded from the exercise tasks.
But from now on, where appropriate, you can
use this.
And similarly "filter", about selecting things
from a list.
That is also something we have done so far
with list comprehensions with these guard
expressions saying: I take each element from
a list which satisfies a predicate (something
like "even a", for example), and then the
"a" is kept.
This is exactly as was described for the filter-function.
So, "map" and "filter" are somehow replacements
for certain kinds of list comprehensions,
at least.
And that is a way to maybe remember, and better
understand, these functions from your perspective
now, because you already know list comprehensions.
But also the opposite is true, namely: conversely,
every list comprehension expression, no matter
how complicated (maybe using several generators,
more than one guard expression, etc.), can
be implemented with "map" and "filter", and
actually, we might use the "concat" function
in addition (which was introduced earlier).
It is not a higher-order function.
It is a polymorphic function which basically
flattens list levels.
So, if we have a list of lists of "a"s, then
"concat" gives us a list of "a"s by concatenating
all the inner lists.
And if you have "map", "filter", and "concat",
then you don't need list comprehensions anymore.
Because whatever you could express with even
complicated list comprehension expressions
can also be expressed with "map", "filter",
and "concat".
And indeed, that is what the compiler does.
So, if in your Haskell code you use list comprehensions,
then at some point during the compilation
process, they essentially get replaced by
expressions involving "map", "filter", and
"concat".
Given this relationship to list comprehensions,
a further question might be whether if we
now switch from list comprehensions to "map"
and "filter" (and maybe "foldl1" and other
similar functions), is this still wholemeal
programming in the sense discussed in the
last week?
So far, my examples on wholemeal programming
were about using list comprehensions instead
of explicit recursion or instead of list indexing.
So, now, if I go to "map" and "filter" and
other higher-order functions, is this still
wholemeal programming?
Yes, absolutely!
In some sense even more so.
Since these higher-order functions provide
a first step in the direction of more abstraction.
As I said, they are available for other data
structures as well.
List comprehensions are for lists.
So, if we want to do wholemeal programming
on lists, we can use list comprehensions.
What about other data structures?
If we have trees or generally not just lists,
but some more structured data structures?
Then we won't have list comprehensions anymore,
because they are about lists.
But these "map" and "filter" and similar functions,
they are available for other data types as
well.
Then we can think about wholemeal programming
on other types as well.
And this is actually a benefit of this more
general perspective.
Discussing this on lists with the "map" and
"filter" versions for lists, I actually want
to discuss a short example.
So, let me first read it here, what the aim
is.
And then we can look at basically two solutions,
with list comprehensions and with "map" and
"filter", and discuss the comparison.
In a similar way to when I compared for-loops
to list comprehension expressions, when I
discussed C versus Haskell in the previous
week.
So, what do we want to do here?
We have some numbers in a list.
We want to square them.
But we want to do that subject to the condition
that we are interested in numbers divisible
by 4.
But what do we mean by "We are interested
in numbers divisible by 4"?
We are not yet clear.
Is it that we want to make sure that we only
square numbers divisible by 4?
Or do we want to check that after we square
the numbers, they are divisible by 4?
That's a subtle difference.
And we want to experiment with both versions.
And we want to look at what does it mean to
express this with list comprehensions (both
ways), and with "map" and "filter".
Let's look at this.
Here are two lists comprehension expressions
for the two cases.
What is the first line saying?
It says: I have a list, I take every element
from the list, I check whether it is divisible
by 4; and if so, I keep it and square it.
This is one of the two versions.
This is the version where I only square numbers
which are divisible by 4.
And the other version is: I decide that what
I want is that the square numbers are divisible
by 4.
So, I want to take the numbers from the list,
and to square them (just in case, to be prepared
to check them), and I do not check the x for
divisibility by 4, but the y (which is the
square of x).
And only if this passes, then I keep the y.
These are the two versions.
And I have to do some work to switch from
one to the other.
It is not an obvious transformation from here
to there, or from here to there.
And the only difference conceptually is:
Do I want to square those things which are
divisible by 4?
Or do I want to square things and the outcome
should be divisible by 4?
This leads to quite different code.
Well, it is not completely different code,
but I had to rearrange this list comprehension.
What is the message here if I do this, instead,
with "map" and "filter"?
It becomes more symmetric, in a way.
Writing this with "map" and "filter", what
would I do?
Well, the first version is: I want to look
at all the values from the original list which
are divisible by 4, then I want to square
them.
But how can I express this?
I can use function composition, which I introduced
in the previous whiteboard video, and compose
two functions, namely uses of "filter" and
"map".
The "filter" function is the one which will
make the job of only keeping the elements
which are divisible by 4.
That's what will happen here.
And afterwards, I will square the elements
in the list which I have at this point, after
filtering.
This is, again, section syntax: the function
that takes something and squares it.
So, this corresponds to the first line here.
And to the second line corresponds what?
Well, here I want to say: I want to square
elements in a list, and I want to only keep
those where the square is divisible by 4.
This, simply, means to switch the order of
the constituents of this function composition.
Now, I first apply "map" to square each element
of my given list.
So, these two expressions will, of course,
be applied to this list.
These are functions after composition.
They are composing functions into a function.
And then, this whole expression, this one
or this one, would be applied to a list.
When we do this here, this list will have
each element squared, and afterwards we will
filter for divisibility by 4.
So, here, on this level of expression, it simply
means to swap the order of function composition.
Whereas on the somewhat lower level of list
comprehensions, we needed more transformation
of syntax to switch from one version to the
other.
In that sense, this is a nicer and more general
way of expressing manipulation of lists or
list elements.
This is also fine, of course, list comprehensions.
But this is more pleasing from an algebraic
perspective.
And interestingly, also when it comes to expressing
algebraic laws, this perspective of higher-order
functions becomes more general and maybe also
more useful.
So, let's recall this law that we mentioned
a while back, about "reverse" and list comprehensions.
Actually, it was discussed already that thanks
to polymorphism, we can also put other completely
polymorphic functions on lists in this place.
And we said something like: "reverse" of a
list comprehension where we apply a function
to each element from a given list (and then
reversing), is the same as doing the same
but on the reversed list, and then not having
the ultimate "reverse" call.
And now that we know that this is basically
a "map" call, we can express this with function
composition, by saying: "reverse after map f
is the same as map f after reverse".
It uses reverse/reverse.
It uses the expression of this list comprehension
by map.
And of course, this is also a "map" call,
namely, on the outcome of "reverse".
And then, if we also use function composition
(this mathematical notion), then we can actually
say: "reverse after map is the same as map
after reverse".
This is also very nice to remember.
And if we also know that this can be replaced
by other polymorphic functions, we get a very
general law.
And since map can also be similarly defined
on other data structures, and polymorphic
functions exist on other data structures,
we can have the same kind of result then also
for other things than lists.
Which wouldn't be clear how to express if
we want to generalize from these list comprehensions
to some other data type.
Because list comprehension syntax does not
exist for other data types.
But "map" and polymorphic functions do.
So, that's one thing, that we can express laws
like this.
Then, of course, we can also ask ourselves:
what about other higher-order functions?
Do they also satisfy such laws?
So, for example, we could ask ourselves:
Now we have "map" and "filter", do they also
commute in some way?
If I have a map-call and a filter-call, can
I also exchange the order of these?
The answer is: not always.
We also have to take into account that maybe
these need to be different predicates, because
the f might change the type of the list elements.
So, it is not even clear that p and q could
have the same types.
So, certainly, they are not simply the same
predicate.
But maybe there is some relationship between
them.
Actually, I would invite you to think a bit
about this, because this will improve your
understanding of what "map" and "filter" are
doing.
I am not going to discuss this now, but it's
a nice thing to consider.
And generally, it can be said and observed
that higher-order functions are themselves
a boon, are of benefit, for this idea of lawful
program construction.
Remember the quote by Richard Bird that I
started the wholemeal programming lecture
with (in last week's lectures).
So, we come full circle here.
Since these higher-order functions are a good
replacement for list comprehensions, and a
good way of writing wholemeal programs, it
makes sense that they have nice properties,
nice laws, and can be used for program construction.
For designing programs from ideas about algebraic
properties, for example.
Again, this is not something we are going
to do here, but that you might see in action
when you see some of the examples and think
about how they are related.